<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2026 03:46:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic Additive Margin Softmax with Hierarchical Information for Speaker Verification</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19709v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihua Fang, Liang He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Speaker embedding learning based on Euclidean space has achieved significant progress, but it is still insufficient in modeling hierarchical information within speaker features. Hyperbolic space, with its negative curvature geometric properties, can efficiently represent hierarchical information within a finite volume, making it more suitable for the feature distribution of speaker embeddings. In this paper, we propose Hyperbolic Softmax (H-Softmax) and Hyperbolic Additive Margin Softmax (HAM-Softmax) based on hyperbolic space&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19709v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:33:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Component-Level Lesioning of Language Models Reveals Clinically Aligned Aphasia Phenotypes</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19723v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Wang, Jichen Zheng, Jingyuan Sun, Yunhao Zhang, Chunyu Ye, Jixing Li, Chengqing Zong, Shaonan Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large language models (LLMs) increasingly exhibit human-like linguistic behaviors and internal representations that they could serve as computational simulators of language cognition. We ask whether LLMs can be systematically manipulated to reproduce language-production impairments characteristic of aphasia following focal brain lesions. Such models could provide scalable proxies for testing rehabilitation hypotheses, and offer a controlled framework for probing the functional organization of language&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19723v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:47:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RvB: Automating AI System Hardening via Iterative Red-Blue Games</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19726v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lige Huang, Zicheng Liu, Jie Zhang, Lewen Yan, Dongrui Liu, Jing Shao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dual offensive and defensive utility of Large Language Models (LLMs) highlights a critical gap in AI security: the lack of unified frameworks for dynamic, iterative adversarial adaptation hardening. To bridge this gap, we propose the Red Team vs. Blue Team (RvB) framework, formulated as a training-free, sequential, imperfect-information game&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19726v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:49:58 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TokenSeek: Memory Efficient Fine Tuning via Instance-Aware Token Ditching</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19739v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Runjia Zeng, Qifan Wang, Qiang Guan, Ruixiang Tang, Lifu Huang, Zhenting Wang, Xueling Zhang, Cheng Han&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fine tuning has been regarded as a de facto approach for adapting large language models (LLMs) to downstream tasks, but the high training memory consumption inherited from LLMs makes this process inefficient. Among existing memory efficient approaches, activation-related optimization has proven particularly effective, as activations consistently dominate overall memory consumption. Although prior arts offer various activation optimization strategies, their data-agnostic nature ultimately results in ineffective and unstable fine tuning&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19739v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 15:58:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Veri-Sure: A Contract-Aware Multi-Agent Framework with Temporal Tracing and Formal Verification for Correct RTL Code Generation</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19747v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiale Liu, Taiyu Zhou, Tianqi Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the rapidly evolving field of Electronic Design Automation (EDA), the deployment of Large Language Models (LLMs) for Register-Transfer Level (RTL) design has emerged as a promising direction. However, silicon-grade correctness remains bottlenecked by: (i) limited test coverage and reliability of simulation-centric evaluation, (ii) regressions and repair hallucinations introduced by iterative debugging, and (iii) semantic drift as intent is reinterpreted across agent handoffs. In this work, we propose Veri-Sure, a multi-agent framework that establishes a design contract to align agents' inte&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19747v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:10:23 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agentic Design Patterns: A System-Theoretic Framework</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19752v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Minh-Dung Dao, Quy Minh Le, Hoang Thanh Lam, Duc-Trong Le, Quoc-Viet Pham, Barry O'Sullivan, Hoang D. Nguyen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the development of foundation model (FM), agentic AI systems are getting more attention, yet their inherent issues like hallucination and poor reasoning, coupled with the frequent ad-hoc nature of system design, lead to unreliable and brittle applications. Existing efforts to characterise agentic design patterns often lack a rigorous systems-theoretic foundation, resulting in high-level or convenience-based taxonomies that are difficult to implement. This paper addresses this gap by introducing a principled methodology for engineering robust AI agents&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19752v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:14:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provable Learning of Random Hierarchy Models and Hierarchical Shallow-to-Deep Chaining</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19756v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yunwei Ren, Yatin Dandi, Florent Krzakala, Jason D. Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The empirical success of deep learning is often attributed to deep networks' ability to exploit hierarchical structure in data, constructing increasingly complex features across layers. Yet despite substantial progress in deep learning theory, most optimization results sill focus on networks with only two or three layers, leaving the theoretical understanding of hierarchical learning in genuinely deep models limited. This leads to a natural question: can we prove that deep networks, trained by gradient-based methods, can efficiently exploit hierarchical structure?   In this work, we consider R&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19756v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:19:54 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GAVEL: Towards rule-based safety through activation monitoring</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19768v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shir Rozenfeld, Rahul Pankajakshan, Itay Zloczower, Eyal Lenga, Gilad Gressel, Yisroel Mirsky&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly paired with activation-based monitoring to detect and prevent harmful behaviors that may not be apparent at the surface-text level. However, existing activation safety approaches, trained on broad misuse datasets, struggle with poor precision, limited flexibility, and lack of interpretability. This paper introduces a new paradigm: rule-based activation safety, inspired by rule-sharing practices in cybersecurity&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19768v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:31:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reimagining Peer Review Process Through Multi-Agent Mechanism Design</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19778v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ahmad Farooq, Kamran Iqbal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The software engineering research community faces a systemic crisis: peer review is failing under growing submissions, misaligned incentives, and reviewer fatigue. Community surveys reveal that researchers perceive the process as "broken." This position paper argues that these dysfunctions are mechanism design failures amenable to computational solutions. We propose modeling the research community as a stochastic multi-agent system and applying multi-agent reinforcement learning to design incentive-compatible protocols&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19778v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:43:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Grok Grokking: Provable Grokking in Ridge Regression</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19791v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mingyue Xu, Gal Vardi, Itay Safran&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study grokking, the onset of generalization long after overfitting, in a classical ridge regression setting. We prove end-to-end grokking results for learning over-parameterized linear regression models using gradient descent with weight decay. Specifically, we prove that the following stages occur: (i) the model overfits the training data early during training; (ii) poor generalization persists long after overfitting has manifested; and (iii) the generalization error eventually becomes arbitrarily small&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19791v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:52:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LVLMs and Humans Ground Differently in Referential Communication</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19792v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Peter Zeng, Weiling Li, Amie Paige, Zhengxiang Wang, Panagiotis Kaliosis, Dimitris Samaras, Gregory Zelinsky, Susan Brennan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For generative AI agents to partner effectively with human users, the ability to accurately predict human intent is critical. But this ability to collaborate remains limited by a critical deficit: an inability to model common ground. Here, we present a referential communication experiment with a factorial design involving director-matcher pairs (human-human, human-AI, AI-human, and AI-AI) that interact with multiple turns in repeated rounds to match pictures of objects not associated with any obvious lexicalized labels&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19792v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:52:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CASTER: Breaking the Cost-Performance Barrier in Multi-Agent Orchestration via Context-Aware Strategy for Task Efficient Routing</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19793v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shanyv Liu, Xuyang Yuan, Tao Chen, Zijun Zhan, Zhu Han, Danyang Zheng, Weishan Zhang, Shaohua Cao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Graph-based Multi-Agent Systems (MAS) enable complex cyclic workflows but suffer from inefficient static model allocation, where deploying strong models uniformly wastes computation on trivial sub-tasks. We propose CASTER (Context-Aware Strategy for Task Efficient Routing), a lightweight router for dynamic model selection in graph-based MAS. CASTER employs a Dual-Signal Router that combines semantic embeddings with structural meta-features to estimate task difficulty&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19793v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 16:52:47 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Incremental Stochastic Majorization-Minimization Algorithms with Applications to Mixture of Experts</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19811v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; TrungKhang Tran, TrungTin Nguyen, Gersende Fort, Tung Doan, Hien Duy Nguyen, Binh T. Nguyen, Florence Forbes, Christopher Drovandi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Processing high-volume, streaming data is increasingly common in modern statistics and machine learning, where batch-mode algorithms are often impractical because they require repeated passes over the full dataset. This has motivated incremental stochastic estimation methods, including the incremental stochastic Expectation-Maximization (EM) algorithm formulated via stochastic approximation. In this work, we revisit and analyze an incremental stochastic variant of the Majorization-Minimization (MM) algorithm, which generalizes incremental stochastic EM as a special case&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Interpretable Recommendation Model for Psychometric Data, With an Application to Gerontological Primary Care</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19824v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andre Paulino de Lima, Paula Castro, Suzana Carvalho Vaz de Andrade, Rosa Maria Marcucci, Ruth Caldeira de Melo, Marcelo Garcia Manzato&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are challenges that must be overcome to make recommender systems useful in healthcare settings. The reasons are varied: the lack of publicly available clinical data, the difficulty that users may have in understanding the reasons why a recommendation was made, the risks that may be involved in following that recommendation, and the uncertainty about its effectiveness. In this work, we address these challenges with a recommendation model that leverages the structure of psychometric data to provide visual explanations that are faithful to the model and interpretable by care professionals&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19824v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Routing End User Queries to Enterprise Databases</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19825v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Saikrishna Sudarshan, Tanay Kulkarni, Manasi Patwardhan, Lovekesh Vig, Ashwin Srinivasan, Tanmay Tulsidas Verlekar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We address the task of routing natural language queries in multi-database enterprise environments. We construct realistic benchmarks by extending existing NL-to-SQL datasets. Our study shows that routing becomes increasingly challenging with larger, domain-overlapping DB repositories and ambiguous queries, motivating the need for more structured and robust reasoning-based solutions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19825v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:30:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Iterative RAG Beats Ideal Evidence: A Diagnostic Study in Scientific Multi-hop Question Answering</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19827v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mahdi Astaraki, Mohammad Arshi Saloot, Ali Shiraee Kasmaee, Hamidreza Mahyar, Soheila Samiee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG) extends large language models (LLMs) beyond parametric knowledge, yet it is unclear when iterative retrieval-reasoning loops meaningfully outperform static RAG, particularly in scientific domains with multi-hop reasoning, sparse domain knowledge, and heterogeneous evidence. We provide the first controlled, mechanism-level diagnostic study of whether synchronized iterative retrieval and reasoning can surpass an idealized static upper bound (Gold Context) RAG. We benchmark eleven state-of-the-art LLMs under three regimes: (i) No Context, measuring reliance on&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19827v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Generation Unlocks Human-Like Reasoning through Multimodal World Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19834v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jialong Wu, Xiaoying Zhang, Hongyi Yuan, Xiangcheng Zhang, Tianhao Huang, Changjing He, Chaoyi Deng, Renrui Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Humans construct internal world models and reason by manipulating the concepts within these models. Recent advances in AI, particularly chain-of-thought (CoT) reasoning, approximate such human cognitive abilities, where world models are believed to be embedded within large language models. Expert-level performance in formal and abstract domains such as mathematics and programming has been achieved in current systems by relying predominantly on verbal reasoning&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19834v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HARMONI: Multimodal Personalization of Multi-User Human-Robot Interactions with LLMs</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19839v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jeanne Malécot, Hamed Rahimi, Jeanne Cattoni, Marie Samson, Mouad Abrini, Mahdi Khoramshahi, Maribel Pino, Mohamed Chetouani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Existing human-robot interaction systems often lack mechanisms for sustained personalization and dynamic adaptation in multi-user environments, limiting their effectiveness in real-world deployments. We present HARMONI, a multimodal personalization framework that leverages large language models to enable socially assistive robots to manage long-term multi-user interactions. The framework integrates four key modules: (i) a perception module that identifies active speakers and extracts multimodal input; (ii) a world modeling module that maintains representations of the environment and short-term&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19839v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 17:45:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI Cap-and-Trade: Efficiency Incentives for Accessibility and Sustainability</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19886v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marco Bornstein, Amrit Singh Bedi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The race for artificial intelligence (AI) dominance often prioritizes scale over efficiency. Hyper-scaling is the common industry approach: larger models, more data, and as many computational resources as possible. Using more resources is a simpler path to improved AI performance&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19886v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:53:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>M-SGWR: Multiscale Similarity and Geographically Weighted Regression</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19888v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; M. Naser Lessani, Zhenlong Li, Manzhu Yu, Helen Greatrex, Chan Shen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first law of geography is a cornerstone of spatial analysis, emphasizing that nearby and related locations tend to be more similar, however, defining what constitutes "near" and "related" remains challenging, as different phenomena exhibit distinct spatial patterns. Traditional local regression models, such as Geographically Weighted Regression (GWR) and Multiscale GWR (MGWR), quantify spatial relationships solely through geographic proximity. In an era of globalization and digital connectivity, however, geographic proximity alone may be insufficient to capture how locations are interconne&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.19888v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 18:55:12 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
