<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 03:12:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>CCSD: Cross-Modal Compositional Self-Distillation for Robust Brain Tumor Segmentation with Missing Modalities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14599v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Dongqing Xie, Yonghuang Wu, Zisheng Ai, Jun Min, Zhencun Jiang, Shaojin Geng, Lei Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The accurate segmentation of brain tumors from multi-modal MRI is critical for clinical diagnosis and treatment planning. While integrating complementary information from various MRI sequences is a common practice, the frequent absence of one or more modalities in real-world clinical settings poses a significant challenge, severely compromising the performance and generalizability of deep learning-based segmentation models. To address this challenge, we propose a novel Cross-Modal Compositional Self-Distillation (CCSD) framework that can flexibly handle arbitrary combinations of input modaliti&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14599v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:39:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MRI Embeddings Complement Clinical Predictors for Cognitive Decline Modeling in Alzheimer's Disease Cohorts</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14601v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nathaniel Putera, Daniel Vilet Rodríguez, Noah Videcrantz, Julia Machnio, Mostafa Mehdipour Ghazi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurate modeling of cognitive decline in Alzheimer's disease is essential for early stratification and personalized management. While tabular predictors provide robust markers of global risk, their ability to capture subtle brain changes remains limited. In this study, we evaluate the predictive contributions of tabular and imaging-based representations, with a focus on transformer-derived Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) embeddings&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14601v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:45:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Method for Characterizing Disease Progression from Acute Kidney Injury to Chronic Kidney Disease</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14603v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yilu Fang, Jordan G. Nestor, Casey N. Ta, Jerard Z. Kneifati-Hayek, Chunhua Weng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Patients with acute kidney injury (AKI) are at high risk of developing chronic kidney disease (CKD), but identifying those at greatest risk remains challenging. We used electronic health record (EHR) data to dynamically track AKI patients' clinical evolution and characterize AKI-to-CKD progression. Post-AKI clinical states were identified by clustering patient vectors derived from longitudinal medical codes and creatinine measurements&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14603v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 15:53:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expert-Guided POMDP Learning for Data-Efficient Modeling in Healthcare</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14619v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marco Locatelli, Arjen Hommersom, Roberto Clemens Cerioli, Daniela Besozzi, Fabio Stella&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learning the parameters of Partially Observable Markov Decision Processes (POMDPs) from limited data is a significant challenge. We introduce the Fuzzy MAP EM algorithm, a novel approach that incorporates expert knowledge into the parameter estimation process by enriching the Expectation Maximization (EM) framework with fuzzy pseudo-counts derived from an expert-defined fuzzy model. This integration naturally reformulates the problem as a Maximum A Posteriori (MAP) estimation, effectively guiding learning in environments with limited data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14619v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:12:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Matter as a framework for living systems-inspired Robophysics</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14624v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Giulia Janzen, Gaia Maselli, Juan F. Jimenez, Lia Garcia-Perez, D A Matoz Fernandez, Chantal Valeriani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robophysics investigates the physical principles that govern living-like robots operating in complex, realworld environments. Despite remarkable technological advances, robots continue to face fundamental efficiency limitations. At the level of individual units, locomotion remains a challenge, while at the collective level, robot swarms struggle to achieve shared purpose, coordination, communication, and cost efficiency&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14624v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:16:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Failure to Mix: Large language models struggle to answer according to desired probability distributions</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14630v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ivy Yuqian Yang, David Yu Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scientific idea generation and selection requires exploration following a target probability distribution. In contrast, current AI benchmarks have objectively correct answers, and training large language models (LLMs) via reinforcement learning against these benchmarks discourages probabilistic exploration. Here, we conducted systematic experiments requesting LLMs to produce outputs following simple probabilistic distributions, and found that all modern LLMs tested grossly fail to follow the distributions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14630v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:22:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Agentic Autonomous Scientific Discovery with Vision-Language Model Capabilities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14631v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kahaan Gandhi, Boris Bolliet, Inigo Zubeldia&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We show that multi-agent systems guided by vision-language models (VLMs) improve end-to-end autonomous scientific discovery. By treating plots as verifiable checkpoints, a VLM-as-a-judge evaluates figures against dynamically generated domain-specific rubrics, enabling agents to correct their own errors and steer exploratory data analysis in real-time. Case studies in cosmology and astrochemistry demonstrate recovery from faulty reasoning paths and adaptation to new datasets without human intervention&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14631v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:23:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adapformer: Adaptive Channel Management for Multivariate Time Series Forecasting</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14632v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuchen Luo, Xinyu Li, Liuhua Peng, Mingming Gong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In multivariate time series forecasting (MTSF), accurately modeling the intricate dependencies among multiple variables remains a significant challenge due to the inherent limitations of traditional approaches. Most existing models adopt either \textbf{channel-independent} (CI) or \textbf{channel-dependent} (CD) strategies, each presenting distinct drawbacks. CI methods fail to leverage the potential insights from inter-channel interactions, resulting in models that may not fully exploit the underlying statistical dependencies present in the data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14632v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:24:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AutoTool: Efficient Tool Selection for Large Language Model Agents</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14650v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingyi Jia, Qinbin Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large Language Model (LLM) agents have emerged as powerful tools for automating complex tasks by leveraging the reasoning and decision-making abilities of LLMs. However, a major bottleneck in current agent frameworks lies in the high inference cost of tool selection, especially in approaches like ReAct that repeatedly invoke the LLM to determine which tool to use at each step. In this work, we propose AutoTool, a novel graph-based framework that bypasses repeated LLM inference by exploiting a key empirical observation: tool usage inertia - the tendency of tool invocations to follow predictable&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14650v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:41:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving segmentation of retinal arteries and veins using cardiac signal in doppler holograms</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14654v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marius Dubosc, Yann Fischer, Zacharie Auray, Nicolas Boutry, Edwin Carlinet, Michael Atlan, Thierry Geraud&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Doppler holography is an emerging retinal imaging technique that captures the dynamic behavior of blood flow with high temporal resolution, enabling quantitative assessment of retinal hemodynamics. This requires accurate segmentation of retinal arteries and veins, but traditional segmentation methods focus solely on spatial information and overlook the temporal richness of holographic data. In this work, we propose a simple yet effective approach for artery-vein segmentation in temporal Doppler holograms using standard segmentation architectures&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14654v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:49:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NORA-1.5: A Vision-Language-Action Model Trained using World Model- and Action-based Preference Rewards</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14659v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chia-Yu Hung, Navonil Majumder, Haoyuan Deng, Liu Renhang, Yankang Ang, Amir Zadeh, Chuan Li, Dorien Herremans&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vision--language--action (VLA) models have recently shown promising performance on a variety of embodied tasks, yet they still fall short in reliability and generalization, especially when deployed across different embodiments or real-world environments. In this work, we introduce NORA-1.5, a VLA model built from the pre-trained NORA backbone by adding to it a flow-matching-based action expert. This architectural enhancement alone yields substantial performance gains, enabling NORA-1.5 to outperform NORA and several state-of-the-art VLA models across both simulated and real-world benchmarks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14659v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 16:55:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SkillGen: Learning Domain Skills for In-Context Sequential Decision Making</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14670v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ruomeng Ding, Wei Cheng, Minglai Shao, Chen Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly applied to sequential decision-making through in-context learning (ICL), yet their effectiveness is highly sensitive to prompt quality. Effective prompts should meet three principles: focus on decision-critical information, provide step-level granularity, and minimize reliance on expert annotations through label efficiency. However, existing ICL methods often fail to satisfy all three criteria simultaneously&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14670v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:09:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground Truth Generation for Multilingual Historical NLP using LLMs</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14688v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Clovis Gladstone, Zhao Fang, Spencer Dean Stewart&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Historical and low-resource NLP remains challenging due to limited annotated data and domain mismatches with modern, web-sourced corpora. This paper outlines our work in using large language models (LLMs) to create ground-truth annotations for historical French (16th-20th centuries) and Chinese (1900-1950) texts. By leveraging LLM-generated ground truth on a subset of our corpus, we were able to fine-tune spaCy to achieve significant gains on period-specific tests for part-of-speech (POS) annotations, lemmatization, and named entity recognition (NER)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14688v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:25:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attention via Synaptic Plasticity is All You Need: A Biologically Inspired Spiking Neuromorphic Transformer</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14691v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kallol Mondal, Ankush Kumar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Attention is the brain's ability to selectively focus on a few specific aspects while ignoring irrelevant ones. This biological principle inspired the attention mechanism in modern Transformers. Transformers now underpin large language models (LLMs) such as GPT, but at the cost of massive training and inference energy, leading to a large carbon footprint&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14691v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:28:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-Lossless Model Compression Enables Longer Context Inference in DNA Large Language Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14694v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rui Zhu, Xiaopu Zhou, Haixu Tang, Stephen W. Scherer, Lucila Ohno-Machado&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trained on massive cross-species DNA corpora, DNA large language models (LLMs) learn the fundamental "grammar" and evolutionary patterns of genomic sequences. This makes them powerful priors for DNA sequence modeling, particularly over long ranges. However, two major constraints hinder their use in practice: the quadratic computational cost of self-attention and the growing memory required for key-value (KV) caches during autoregressive decoding&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14694v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:29:39 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Beyond the Image: ECG and Anatomical Knowledge-Guided Myocardial Scar Segmentation from Late Gadolinium-Enhanced Images</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14702v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Farheen Ramzan, Yusuf Kiberu, Nikesh Jathanna, Meryem Jabrane, Vicente Grau, Shahnaz Jamil-Copley, Richard H. Clayton, Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurate segmentation of myocardial scar from late gadolinium enhanced (LGE) cardiac MRI is essential for evaluating tissue viability, yet remains challenging due to variable contrast and imaging artifacts. Electrocardiogram (ECG) signals provide complementary physiological information, as conduction abnormalities can help localize or suggest scarred myocardial regions. In this work, we propose a novel multimodal framework that integrates ECG-derived electrophysiological information with anatomical priors from the AHA-17 atlas for physiologically consistent LGE-based scar segmentation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14702v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:42:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>\textit{FLARE}: Adaptive Multi-Dimensional Reputation for Robust Client Reliability in Federated Learning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14715v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abolfazl Younesi, Leon Kiss, Zahra Najafabadi Samani, Juan Aznar Poveda, Thomas Fahringer&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Federated learning (FL) enables collaborative model training while preserving data privacy. However, it remains vulnerable to malicious clients who compromise model integrity through Byzantine attacks, data poisoning, or adaptive adversarial behaviors. Existing defense mechanisms rely on static thresholds and binary classification, failing to adapt to evolving client behaviors in real-world deployments&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14715v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 17:57:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-shot Synthetic Video Realism Enhancement via Structure-aware Denoising</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14719v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yifan Wang, Liya Ji, Zhanghan Ke, Harry Yang, Ser-Nam Lim, Qifeng Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We propose an approach to enhancing synthetic video realism, which can re-render synthetic videos from a simulator in photorealistic fashion. Our realism enhancement approach is a zero-shot framework that focuses on preserving the multi-level structures from synthetic videos into the enhanced one in both spatial and temporal domains, built upon a diffusion video foundational model without further fine-tuning. Specifically, we incorporate an effective modification to have the generation/denoising process conditioned on estimated structure-aware information from the synthetic video, such as dept&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14719v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 18:06:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look-Ahead Reasoning on Learning Platforms</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14745v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haiqing Zhu, Tijana Zrnic, Celestine Mendler-Dünner&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;On many learning platforms, the optimization criteria guiding model training reflect the priorities of the designer rather than those of the individuals they affect. Consequently, users may act strategically to obtain more favorable outcomes, effectively contesting the platform's predictions. While past work has studied strategic user behavior on learning platforms, the focus has largely been on strategic responses to a deployed model, without considering the behavior of other users&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14745v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 18:45:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ARC Is a Vision Problem!</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14761v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Keya Hu, Ali Cy, Linlu Qiu, Xiaoman Delores Ding, Runqian Wang, Yeyin Eva Zhu, Jacob Andreas, Kaiming He&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Abstraction and Reasoning Corpus (ARC) is designed to promote research on abstract reasoning, a fundamental aspect of human intelligence. Common approaches to ARC treat it as a language-oriented problem, addressed by large language models (LLMs) or recurrent reasoning models. However, although the puzzle-like tasks in ARC are inherently visual, existing research has rarely approached the problem from a vision-centric perspective&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.14761v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 18:59:49 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
