<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 03:25:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Uncertainty in Machine Learning-Based Pervasive Systems: Application to Human Activity Recognition</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09775v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vladimir Balditsyn, Philippe Lalanda, German Vega, Stéphanie Chollet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recent convergence of pervasive computing and machine learning has given rise to numerous services, impacting almost all areas of economic and social activity. However, the use of AI techniques precludes certain standard software development practices, which emphasize rigorous testing to ensure the elimination of all bugs and adherence to well-defined specifications. ML models are trained on numerous high-dimensional examples rather than being manually coded&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09775v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 15:56:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PathCo-LatticE: Pathology-Constrained Lattice-Of Experts Framework for Fully-supervised Few-Shot Cardiac MRI Segmentation</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09779v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Mohamed Elbayumi, Mohammed S. M. Elbaz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Few-shot learning (FSL) mitigates data scarcity in cardiac MRI segmentation but typically relies on semi-supervised techniques sensitive to domain shifts and validation bias, restricting zero-shot generalizability. We propose PathCo-LatticE, a fully supervised FSL framework that replaces unlabeled data with pathology-guided synthetic supervision. First, our Virtual Patient Engine models continuous latent disease trajectories from sparse clinical anchors, using generative modeling to synthesize physiologically plausible, fully labeled 3D cohorts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09779v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 15:59:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHEM: Estimating and Understanding Hallucinations in Deep Learning for Image Processing</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09806v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jianfei Li, Ines Rosellon-Inclan, Gitta Kutyniok, Jean-Luc Starck&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;U-Net and other U-shaped architectures have achieved significant success in image deconvolution tasks. However, challenges have emerged, as these methods might generate unrealistic artifacts or hallucinations, which can interfere with analysis in safety-critical scenarios. This paper introduces a novel approach for quantifying and comprehending hallucination artifacts to ensure trustworthy computer vision models&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09806v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composing Concepts from Images and Videos via Concept-prompt Binding</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09824v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xianghao Kong, Zeyu Zhang, Yuwei Guo, Zhuoran Zhao, Songchun Zhang, Anyi Rao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visual concept composition, which aims to integrate different elements from images and videos into a single, coherent visual output, still falls short in accurately extracting complex concepts from visual inputs and flexibly combining concepts from both images and videos. We introduce Bind &amp; Compose, a one-shot method that enables flexible visual concept composition by binding visual concepts with corresponding prompt tokens and composing the target prompt with bound tokens from various sources. It adopts a hierarchical binder structure for cross-attention conditioning in Diffusion Transformer&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09824v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RIFT: A Scalable Methodology for LLM Accelerator Fault Assessment using Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09829v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khurram Khalil, Muhammad Mahad Khaliq, Khaza Anuarul Hoque&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The massive scale of modern AI accelerators presents critical challenges to traditional fault assessment methodologies, which face prohibitive computational costs and provide poor coverage of critical failure modes. This paper introduces RIFT (Reinforcement Learning-guided Intelligent Fault Targeting), a scalable framework that automates the discovery of minimal, high-impact fault scenarios for efficient design-time fault assessment. RIFT transforms the complex search for worst-case faults into a sequential decision-making problem, combining hybrid sensitivity analysis for search space pruning&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09829v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:07:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs in Interpreting Legal Documents</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09830v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Simone Corbo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This chapter explores the application of Large Language Models in the legal domain, showcasing their potential to optimise and augment traditional legal tasks by analysing possible use cases, such as assisting in interpreting statutes, contracts, and case law, enhancing clarity in legal summarisation, contract negotiation, and information retrieval. There are several challenges that can arise from the application of such technologies, such as algorithmic monoculture, hallucinations, and compliance with existing regulations, including the EU's AI Act and recent U.S. initiatives, alongside the e&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09830v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretation as Linear Transformation: A Cognitive-Geometric Model of Belief and Meaning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09831v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chainarong Amornbunchornvej&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This paper develops a geometric framework for modeling belief, motivation, and influence across cognitively heterogeneous agents. Each agent is represented by a personalized value space, a vector space encoding the internal dimensions through which the agent interprets and evaluates meaning. Beliefs are formalized as structured vectors-abstract beings-whose transmission is mediated by linear interpretation maps&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09831v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:13:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedForget: Hierarchy-Aware Multimodal Unlearning Testbed for Medical AI</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09867v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fengli Wu, Vaidehi Patil, Jaehong Yoon, Yue Zhang, Mohit Bansal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pretrained Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) are increasingly deployed in medical AI systems for clinical reasoning, diagnosis support, and report generation. However, their training on sensitive patient data raises critical privacy and compliance challenges under regulations such as HIPAA and GDPR, which enforce the "right to be forgotten". Unlearning, the process of tuning models to selectively remove the influence of specific training data points, offers a potential solution, yet its effectiveness in complex medical settings remains underexplored&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09867v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:55:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlipLLM: Efficient Bit-Flip Attacks on Multimodal LLMs using Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09872v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Khurram Khalil, Khaza Anuarul Hoque&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generative Artificial Intelligence models, such as Large Language Models (LLMs) and Large Vision Models (VLMs), exhibit state-of-the-art performance but remain vulnerable to hardware-based threats, specifically bit-flip attacks (BFAs). Existing BFA discovery methods lack generalizability and struggle to scale, often failing to analyze the vast parameter space and complex interdependencies of modern foundation models in a reasonable time. This paper proposes FlipLLM, a reinforcement learning (RL) architecture-agnostic framework that formulates BFA discovery as a sequential decision-making probl&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09872v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 17:58:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparing AI Agents to Cybersecurity Professionals in Real-World Penetration Testing</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09882v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Justin W. Lin, Eliot Krzysztof Jones, Donovan Julian Jasper, Ethan Jun-shen Ho, Anna Wu, Arnold Tianyi Yang, Neil Perry, Andy Zou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We present the first comprehensive evaluation of AI agents against human cybersecurity professionals in a live enterprise environment. We evaluate ten cybersecurity professionals alongside six existing AI agents and ARTEMIS, our new agent scaffold, on a large university network consisting of ~8,000 hosts across 12 subnets. ARTEMIS is a multi-agent framework featuring dynamic prompt generation, arbitrary sub-agents, and automatic vulnerability triaging&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09882v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:12:29 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Provably Learning from Modern Language Models via Low Logit Rank</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09892v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Noah Golowich, Allen Liu, Abhishek Shetty&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While modern language models and their inner workings are incredibly complex, recent work (Golowich, Liu &amp; Shetty; 2025) has proposed a simple and potentially tractable abstraction for them through the observation that empirically, these language models all seem to have approximately low logit rank. Roughly, this means that a matrix formed by the model's log probabilities of various tokens conditioned on certain sequences of tokens is well approximated by a low rank matrix.   In this paper, our focus is on understanding how this structure can be exploited algorithmically for obtaining provable&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09892v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:18:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-in-the-Loop and AI: Crowdsourcing Metadata Vocabulary for Materials Science</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09895v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jane Greenberg, Scott McClellan, Addy Ireland, Robert Sammarco, Colton Gerber, Christopher B. Rauch, Mat Kelly, John Kunze&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Metadata vocabularies are essential for advancing FAIR and FARR data principles, but their development constrained by limited human resources and inconsistent standardization practices. This paper introduces MatSci-YAMZ, a platform that integrates artificial intelligence (AI) and human-in-the-loop (HILT), including crowdsourcing, to support metadata vocabulary development. The paper reports on a proof-of-concept use case evaluating the AI-HILT model in materials science, a highly interdisciplinary domain Six (6) participants affiliated with the NSF Institute for Data-Driven Dynamical Design (I&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09895v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:22:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SCOPE: Language Models as One-Time Teacher for Hierarchical Planning in Text Environments</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09897v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Haoye Lu, Pavan Seshadri, Kaheer Suleman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Long-term planning in complex, text-based environments presents significant challenges due to open-ended action spaces, ambiguous observations, and sparse feedback. Recent research suggests that large language models (LLMs) encode rich semantic knowledge about the world, which can be valuable for guiding agents in high-level reasoning and planning across both embodied and purely textual settings. However, existing approaches often depend heavily on querying LLMs during training and inference, making them computationally expensive and difficult to deploy efficiently&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09897v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visual Heading Prediction for Autonomous Aerial Vehicles</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09898v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Reza Ahmari, Ahmad Mohammadi, Vahid Hemmati, Mohammed Mynuddin, Parham Kebria, Mahmoud Nabil Mahmoud, Xiaohong Yuan, Abdollah Homaifar&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The integration of Unmanned Aerial Vehicles (UAVs) and Unmanned Ground Vehicles (UGVs) is increasingly central to the development of intelligent autonomous systems for applications such as search and rescue, environmental monitoring, and logistics. However, precise coordination between these platforms in real-time scenarios presents major challenges, particularly when external localization infrastructure such as GPS or GNSS is unavailable or degraded [1]. This paper proposes a vision-based, data-driven framework for real-time UAV-UGV integration, with a focus on robust UGV detection and headin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09898v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:27:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Networks, Markov Networks, Moralisation, Triangulation: a Categorical Perspective</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09908v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Antonio Lorenzin, Fabio Zanasi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Moralisation and Triangulation are transformations allowing to switch between different ways of factoring a probability distribution into a graphical model. Moralisation allows to view a Bayesian network (a directed model) as a Markov network (an undirected model), whereas triangulation addresses the opposite direction. We present a categorical framework where these transformations are modelled as functors between a category of Bayesian networks and one of Markov networks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09908v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:36:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>STACHE: Local Black-Box Explanations for Reinforcement Learning Policies</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09909v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Andrew Elashkin, Orna Grumberg&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning agents often behave unexpectedly in sparse-reward or safety-critical environments, creating a strong need for reliable debugging and verification tools. In this paper, we propose STACHE, a comprehensive framework for generating local, black-box explanations for an agent's specific action within discrete Markov games. Our method produces a Composite Explanation consisting of two complementary components: (1) a Robustness Region, the connected neighborhood of states where the agent's action remains invariant, and (2) Minimal Counterfactuals, the smallest state perturbation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09909v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:37:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Continual Learning in Neural Machine Translation: A Low-Rank Adaptation Approach</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09910v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Salvador Carrión, Francisco Casacuberta&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Continual learning in Neural Machine Translation (NMT) faces the dual challenges of catastrophic forgetting and the high computational cost of retraining. This study establishes Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) as a parameter-efficient framework to address these challenges in dedicated NMT architectures. We first demonstrate that LoRA-based fine-tuning adapts NMT models to new languages and domains with performance on par with full-parameter techniques, while utilizing only a fraction of the parameter space&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09910v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supervised learning pays attention</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09912v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Erin Craig, Robert Tibshirani&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In-context learning with attention enables large neural networks to make context-specific predictions by selectively focusing on relevant examples. Here, we adapt this idea to supervised learning procedures such as lasso regression and gradient boosting, for tabular data. Our goals are to (1) flexibly fit personalized models for each prediction point and (2) retain model simplicity and interpretability&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09912v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:43:46 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FALCON: Few-step Accurate Likelihoods for Continuous Flows</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09914v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Danyal Rehman, Tara Akhound-Sadegh, Artem Gazizov, Yoshua Bengio, Alexander Tong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scalable sampling of molecular states in thermodynamic equilibrium is a long-standing challenge in statistical physics. Boltzmann Generators tackle this problem by pairing a generative model, capable of exact likelihood computation, with importance sampling to obtain consistent samples under the target distribution. Current Boltzmann Generators primarily use continuous normalizing flows (CNFs) trained with flow matching for efficient training of powerful models&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09914v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:47:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Model Intercomparison Study of Mixed-Phase Clouds in a Laboratory Chamber</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09915v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Aaron Wang, Sisi Chen, Steve Krueger, Piotr Dziekan, Kotaro Enokido, Fabian Hoffmann, Agnieszka Makulska, Bernhard Mehlig&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mixed-phase clouds, composed of supercooled liquid droplets and ice crystals, play a critical role in weather and climate systems. Their complex microphysical interactions and coupling with turbulence at microscales govern the cloud properties at macroscales, yet remain challenging to observe and quantify under atmospheric conditions. This model intercomparison study utilizes ten model configurations to simulate mixed-phase cloud evolution in the Michigan Technological University's Pi Chamber&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2512.09915v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 18:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
