<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 03:48:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Ability of Explanations to Disambiguate Models in a Rashomon Set</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08703v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaivalya Rawal, Eoin Delaney, Zihao Fu, Sandra Wachter, Chris Russell&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Explainable artificial intelligence (XAI) is concerned with producing explanations indicating the inner workings of models. For a Rashomon set of similarly performing models, explanations provide a way of disambiguating the behavior of individual models, helping select models for deployment. However explanations themselves can vary depending on the explainer used, and need to be evaluated&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08703v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:31:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Localization Framework for Autonomous Basketball Robots</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08713v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Naren Medarametla, Sreejon Mondal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Localization is a fundamental capability for autonomous robots, enabling them to operate effectively in dynamic environments. In Robocon 2025, accurate and reliable localization is crucial for improving shooting precision, avoiding collisions with other robots, and navigating the competition field efficiently. In this paper, we propose a hybrid localization algorithm that integrates classical techniques with learning based methods that rely solely on visual data from the court's floor to achieve self-localization on the basketball field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08713v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 16:40:18 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ISLA: A U-Net for MRI-based acute ischemic stroke lesion segmentation with deep supervision, attention, domain adaptation, and ensemble learning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08732v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Vincent Roca, Martin Bretzner, Hilde Henon, Laurent Puy, Grégory Kuchcinski, Renaud Lopes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurate delineation of acute ischemic stroke lesions in MRI is a key component of stroke diagnosis and management. In recent years, deep learning models have been successfully applied to the automatic segmentation of such lesions. While most proposed architectures are based on the U-Net framework, they primarily differ in their choice of loss functions and in the use of deep supervision, residual connections, and attention mechanisms&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08732v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:05:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TerraFormer: Automated Infrastructure-as-Code with LLMs Fine-Tuned via Policy-Guided Verifier Feedback</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08734v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Prithwish Jana, Sam Davidson, Bhavana Bhasker, Andrey Kan, Anoop Deoras, Laurent Callot&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Automating Infrastructure-as-Code (IaC) is challenging, and large language models (LLMs) often produce incorrect configurations from natural language (NL). We present TerraFormer, a neuro-symbolic framework for IaC generation and mutation that combines supervised fine-tuning with verifier-guided reinforcement learning, using formal verification tools to provide feedback on syntax, deployability, and policy compliance. We curate two large, high-quality NL-to-IaC datasets, TF-Gen (152k instances) and TF-Mutn (52k instances), via multi-stage verification and iterative LLM self-correction&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08734v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:08:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TableCache: Primary Foreign Key Guided KV Cache Precomputation for Low Latency Text-to-SQL</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08743v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinbo Su, Yuxuan Hu, Cuiping Li, Hong Chen, Jia Li, Lintao Ma, Jing Zhang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In Text-to-SQL tasks, existing LLM-based methods often include extensive database schemas in prompts, leading to long context lengths and increased prefilling latency. While user queries typically focus on recurrent table sets-offering an opportunity for KV cache sharing across queries-current inference engines, such as SGLang and vLLM, generate redundant prefix cache copies when processing user queries with varying table orders. To address this inefficiency, we propose precomputing table representations as KV caches offline and querying the required ones online&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08743v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:20:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grid-Aware Charging and Operational Optimization for Mixed-Fleet Public Transit</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08753v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rishav Sen, Amutheezan Sivagnanam, Aron Laszka, Ayan Mukhopadhyay, Abhishek Dubey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapid growth of urban populations and the increasing need for sustainable transportation solutions have prompted a shift towards electric buses in public transit systems. However, the effective management of mixed fleets consisting of both electric and diesel buses poses significant operational challenges. One major challenge is coping with dynamic electricity pricing, where charging costs vary throughout the day&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08753v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AI as Entertainment</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08768v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Cody Kommers, Ari Holtzman&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Generative AI systems are predominantly designed, evaluated, and marketed as intelligent systems which will benefit society by augmenting or automating human cognitive labor, promising to increase personal, corporate, and macroeconomic productivity. But this mainstream narrative about what AI is and what it can do is in tension with another emerging use case: entertainment. We argue that the field of AI is unprepared to measure or respond to how the proliferation of entertaining AI-generated content will impact society&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08768v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 17:55:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translating Light-Sheet Microscopy Images to Virtual H&amp;E Using CycleGAN</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08776v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yanhua Zhao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Histopathology analysis relies on Hematoxylin and Eosin (H&amp;E) staining, but fluorescence microscopy offers complementary information. Converting fluorescence images to H&amp;E-like appearance can aid interpretation and integration with standard workflows. We present a Cycle-Consistent Adversarial Network (CycleGAN) approach for unpaired image-to-image translation from multi-channel fluorescence microscopy to pseudo H&amp;E stained histopathology images&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08776v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Universal Alignment: A New Alignment Framework via Test-Time Scaling</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08777v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yang Cai, Weiqiang Zheng&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aligning large language models (LLMs) to serve users with heterogeneous and potentially conflicting preferences is a central challenge for personalized and trustworthy AI. We formalize an ideal notion of universal alignment through test-time scaling: for each prompt, the model produces $k\ge 1$ candidate responses and a user selects their preferred one. We introduce $(k,f(k))$-robust alignment, which requires the $k$-output model to have win rate $f(k)$ against any other single-output model, and asymptotic universal alignment (U-alignment), which requires $f(k)\to 1$ as $k\to\infty$&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08777v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:08:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pervasive Annotation Errors Break Text-to-SQL Benchmarks and Leaderboards</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08778v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tengjun Jin, Yoojin Choi, Yuxuan Zhu, Daniel Kang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Researchers have proposed numerous text-to-SQL techniques to streamline data analytics and accelerate the development of database-driven applications. To compare these techniques and select the best one for deployment, the community depends on public benchmarks and their leaderboards. Since these benchmarks heavily rely on human annotations during question construction and answer evaluation, the validity of the annotations is crucial&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08778v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:09:06 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the use of graph models to achieve individual and group fairness</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08784v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Arturo Pérez-Peralta, Sandra Benítez-Peña, Rosa E. Lillo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning algorithms are ubiquitous in key decision-making contexts such as justice, healthcare and finance, which has spawned a great demand for fairness in these procedures. However, the theoretical properties of such models in relation with fairness are still poorly understood, and the intuition behind the relationship between group and individual fairness is still lacking. In this paper, we provide a theoretical framework based on Sheaf Diffusion to leverage tools based on dynamical systems and homology to model fairness&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08784v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:17:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering Political Bias in Large Language Models using Parliamentary Voting Records</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08785v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jieying Chen, Karen de Jong, Andreas Poole, Jan Burakowski, Elena Elderson Nosti, Joep Windt, Chendi Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As large language models (LLMs) become deeply embedded in digital platforms and decision-making systems, concerns about their political biases have grown. While substantial work has examined social biases such as gender and race, systematic studies of political bias remain limited, despite their direct societal impact. This paper introduces a general methodology for constructing political bias benchmarks by aligning model-generated voting predictions with verified parliamentary voting records&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08785v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:18:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collapse of statistical equilibrium in large-scale hydroelastic turbulent waves</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08799v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Marlone Vernet, Eric Falcon&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At scales larger than the forcing scale, some out-of-equilibrium turbulent systems (such as hydrodynamic turbulence, wave turbulence, and nonlinear optics) exhibit a state of statistical equilibrium where energy is equipartitioned among large-scale modes, in line with the Rayleigh-Jeans spectrum. Key open questions now pertain to either the emergence, decay, collapse, or other nonstationary evolutions from this state. Here, we experimentally investigate the free decay of large-scale hydroelastic turbulent waves, initially in a regime of statistical equilibrium&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08799v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:35:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APEX-SWE</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08806v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abhi Kottamasu, Akul Datta, Aakash Barthwal, Chirag Mahapatra, Ajay Arun, Adarsh Hiremath, Brendan Foody, Bertie Vidgen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce the AI Productivity Index for Software Engineering (APEX-SWE), a benchmark for assessing whether frontier AI models can execute economically valuable software engineering work. Unlike existing evaluations that focus on narrow, well-defined tasks, APEX-SWE assesses two novel task types that reflect real-world software engineering work: (1) Integration tasks (n=100), which require constructing end-to-end systems across heterogeneous cloud primitives, business applications, and infrastructure-as-code services, and (2) Observability tasks (n=100), which require debugging production fa&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08806v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:44:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>S3-CLIP: Video Super Resolution for Person-ReID</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08807v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tamas Endrei, Gyorgy Cserey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tracklet quality is often treated as an afterthought in most person re-identification (ReID) methods, with the majority of research presenting architectural modifications to foundational models. Such approaches neglect an important limitation, posing challenges when deploying ReID systems in real-world, difficult scenarios. In this paper, we introduce S3-CLIP, a video super-resolution-based CLIP-ReID framework developed for the VReID-XFD challenge at WACV 2026&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08807v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:46:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplex Thinking: Reasoning via Token-wise Branch-and-Merge</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08808v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yao Tang, Li Dong, Yaru Hao, Qingxiu Dong, Furu Wei, Jiatao Gu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large language models often solve complex reasoning tasks more effectively with Chain-of-Thought (CoT), but at the cost of long, low-bandwidth token sequences. Humans, by contrast, often reason softly by maintaining a distribution over plausible next steps. Motivated by this, we propose Multiplex Thinking, a stochastic soft reasoning mechanism that, at each thinking step, samples K candidate tokens and aggregates their embeddings into a single continuous multiplex token&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08808v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning Matters for 3D Visual Grounding</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08811v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hsiang-Wei Huang, Kuang-Ming Chen, Wenhao Chai, Cheng-Yen Yang, Jen-Hao Cheng, Jenq-Neng Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The recent development of Large Language Models (LLMs) with strong reasoning ability has driven research in various domains such as mathematics, coding, and scientific discovery. Meanwhile, 3D visual grounding, as a fundamental task in 3D understanding, still remains challenging due to the limited reasoning ability of recent 3D visual grounding models. Most of the current methods incorporate a text encoder and visual feature encoder to generate cross-modal fuse features and predict the referring object&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:48:41 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MemRec: Collaborative Memory-Augmented Agentic Recommender System</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08816v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Weixin Chen, Yuhan Zhao, Jingyuan Huang, Zihe Ye, Clark Mingxuan Ju, Tong Zhao, Neil Shah, Li Chen&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evolution of recommender systems has shifted preference storage from rating matrices and dense embeddings to semantic memory in the agentic era. Yet existing agents rely on isolated memory, overlooking crucial collaborative signals. Bridging this gap is hindered by the dual challenges of distilling vast graph contexts without overwhelming reasoning agents with cognitive load, and evolving the collaborative memory efficiently without incurring prohibitive computational costs&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08816v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:51:16 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motion Attribution for Video Generation</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08828v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xindi Wu, Despoina Paschalidou, Jun Gao, Antonio Torralba, Laura Leal-Taixé, Olga Russakovsky, Sanja Fidler, Jonathan Lorraine&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite the rapid progress of video generation models, the role of data in influencing motion is poorly understood. We present Motive (MOTIon attribution for Video gEneration), a motion-centric, gradient-based data attribution framework that scales to modern, large, high-quality video datasets and models. We use this to study which fine-tuning clips improve or degrade temporal dynamics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08828v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:59:09 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling LLM Agent Reviewer Dynamics in Elo-Ranked Review System</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08829v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hsiang-Wei Huang, Junbin Lu, Kuang-Ming Chen, Jenq-Neng Hwang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this work, we explore the Large Language Model (LLM) agent reviewer dynamics in an Elo-ranked review system using real-world conference paper submissions. Multiple LLM agent reviewers with different personas are engage in multi round review interactions moderated by an Area Chair. We compare a baseline setting with conditions that incorporate Elo ratings and reviewer memory&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.08829v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 18:59:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
