<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 04:22:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Retrieve Navigable Candidates for Efficient Vision-and-Language Navigation</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15724v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shutian Gu, Chengkai Huang, Ruoyu Wang, Lina Yao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vision-and-Language Navigation (VLN) requires an agent to follow natural-language instructions and navigate through previously unseen environments. Recent approaches increasingly employ large language models (LLMs) as high-level navigators due to their flexibility and reasoning capability. However, prompt-based LLM navigation often suffers from inefficient decision-making, as the model must repeatedly interpret instructions from scratch and reason over noisy and verbose navigable candidates at each step&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15724v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:00:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recursive Concept Evolution for Compositional Reasoning in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15725v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sarim Chaudhry&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large language models achieve strong performance on many complex reasoning tasks, yet their accuracy degrades sharply on benchmarks that require compositional reasoning, including ARC-AGI-2, GPQA, MATH, BBH, and HLE. Existing methods improve reasoning by expanding token-level search through chain-of-thought prompting, self-consistency, or reinforcement learning, but they leave the model's latent representation space fixed. When the required abstraction is not already encoded in this space, performance collapses&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15725v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:01:42 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spanning the Visual Analogy Space with a Weight Basis of LoRAs</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15727v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Hila Manor, Rinon Gal, Haggai Maron, Tomer Michaeli, Gal Chechik&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visual analogy learning enables image manipulation through demonstration rather than textual description, allowing users to specify complex transformations difficult to articulate in words. Given a triplet $\{\mathbf{a}$, $\mathbf{a}'$, $\mathbf{b}\}$, the goal is to generate $\mathbf{b}'$ such that $\mathbf{a} : \mathbf{a}' :: \mathbf{b} : \mathbf{b}'$. Recent methods adapt text-to-image models to this task using a single Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA) module, but they face a fundamental limitation: attempting to capture the diverse space of visual transformations within a fixed adaptation module&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15727v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:02:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeshMimic: Geometry-Aware Humanoid Motion Learning through 3D Scene Reconstruction</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15733v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qiang Zhang, Jiahao Ma, Peiran Liu, Shuai Shi, Zeran Su, Zifan Wang, Jingkai Sun, Wei Cui&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Humanoid motion control has witnessed significant breakthroughs in recent years, with deep reinforcement learning (RL) emerging as a primary catalyst for achieving complex, human-like behaviors. However, the high dimensionality and intricate dynamics of humanoid robots make manual motion design impractical, leading to a heavy reliance on expensive motion capture (MoCap) data. These datasets are not only costly to acquire but also frequently lack the necessary geometric context of the surrounding physical environment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15733v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:09:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MRC-GAT: A Meta-Relational Copula-Based Graph Attention Network for Interpretable Multimodal Alzheimer's Disease Diagnosis</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15740v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fatemeh Khalvandi, Saadat Izadi, Abdolah Chalechale&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer's disease (AD) is a progressive neurodegenerative condition necessitating early and precise diagnosis to provide prompt clinical management. Given the paramount importance of early diagnosis, recent studies have increasingly focused on computer-aided diagnostic models to enhance precision and reliability. However, most graph-based approaches still rely on fixed structural designs, which restrict their flexibility and limit generalization across heterogeneous patient data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15740v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:15:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UrbanVerse: Learning Urban Region Representation Across Cities and Tasks</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15750v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Fengze Sun, Egemen Tanin, Shanika Karunasekera, Zuqing Li, Flora D. Salim, Jianzhong Qi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent advances in urban region representation learning have enabled a wide range of applications in urban analytics, yet existing methods remain limited in their capabilities to generalize across cities and analytic tasks. We aim to generalize urban representation learning beyond city- and task-specific settings, towards a foundation-style model for urban analytics. To this end, we propose UrbanVerse, a model for cross-city urban representation learning and cross-task urban analytics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15750v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:28:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChartEditBench: Evaluating Grounded Multi-Turn Chart Editing in Multimodal Language Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15758v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Manav Nitin Kapadnis, Lawanya Baghel, Atharva Naik, Carolyn Rosé&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While Multimodal Large Language Models (MLLMs) perform strongly on single-turn chart generation, their ability to support real-world exploratory data analysis remains underexplored. In practice, users iteratively refine visualizations through multi-turn interactions that require maintaining common ground, tracking prior edits, and adapting to evolving preferences. We introduce ChartEditBench, a benchmark for incremental, visually grounded chart editing via code, comprising 5,000 difficulty-controlled modification chains and a rigorously human-verified subset&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15758v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:45:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robot-Assisted Social Dining as a White Glove Service</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15767v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Atharva S Kashyap, Ugne Aleksandra Morkute, Patricia Alves-Oliveira&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Robot-assisted feeding enables people with disabilities who require assistance eating to enjoy a meal independently and with dignity. However, existing systems have only been tested in-lab or in-home, leaving in-the-wild social dining contexts (e.g., restaurants) largely unexplored. Designing a robot for such contexts presents unique challenges, such as dynamic and unsupervised dining environments that a robot needs to account for and respond to&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15767v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 17:58:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Southern Ocean latent heat flux variability driven by oceanic meso- and submesoscale motions</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15768v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Lucie Reymondet, Lia Siegelman, Luc Lenain&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Latent heat flux is a primary pathway for ocean-atmosphere exchange of heat and moisture, yet the influence of sea surface temperature variability at fine scales ($\leq$ 100 km) on latent heat flux variability, particularly over the Southern Ocean, remains poorly understood. Here we quantify the scale-dependent drivers of latent heat flux (LHF) variability using a year-long, global, fully coupled ocean-atmosphere simulation with kilometer-scale resolution. Annual-mean LHF in eddy-rich regions reaches $\approx$ 215 W m$^{-2}$, approximately three times larger than in eddy-poor regions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15768v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:01:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding vs. Generation: Navigating Optimization Dilemma in Multimodal Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15772v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Sen Ye, Mengde Xu, Shuyang Gu, Di He, Liwei Wang, Han Hu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Current research in multimodal models faces a key challenge where enhancing generative capabilities often comes at the expense of understanding, and vice versa. We analyzed this trade-off and identify the primary cause might be the potential conflict between generation and understanding, which creates a competitive dynamic within the model. To address this, we propose the Reason-Reflect-Refine (R3) framework&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15772v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:04:13 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GlobeDiff: State Diffusion Process for Partial Observability in Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15776v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yiqin Yang, Xu Yang, Yuhua Jiang, Ni Mu, Hao Hu, Runpeng Xie, Ziyou Zhang, Siyuan Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the realm of multi-agent systems, the challenge of \emph{partial observability} is a critical barrier to effective coordination and decision-making. Existing approaches, such as belief state estimation and inter-agent communication, often fall short. Belief-based methods are limited by their focus on past experiences without fully leveraging global information, while communication methods often lack a robust model to effectively utilize the auxiliary information they provide&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15776v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:05:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This human study did not involve human subjects: Validating LLM simulations as behavioral evidence</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15785v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jessica Hullman, David Broska, Huaman Sun, Aaron Shaw&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A growing literature uses large language models (LLMs) as synthetic participants to generate cost-effective and nearly instantaneous responses in social science experiments. However, there is limited guidance on when such simulations support valid inference about human behavior. We contrast two strategies for obtaining valid estimates of causal effects and clarify the assumptions under which each is suitable for exploratory versus confirmatory research&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15785v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Building Semantics Preservation in AI Model Training with Large Language Model Encodings</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15791v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Suhyung Jang, Ghang Lee, Jaekun Lee, Hyunjun Lee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accurate representation of building semantics, encompassing both generic object types and specific subtypes, is essential for effective AI model training in the architecture, engineering, construction, and operation (AECO) industry. Conventional encoding methods (e.g., one-hot) often fail to convey the nuanced relationships among closely related subtypes, limiting AI's semantic comprehension. To address this limitation, this study proposes a novel training approach that employs large language model (LLM) embeddings (e.g., OpenAI GPT and Meta LLaMA) as encodings to preserve finer distinctions i&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15791v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:26:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Geometry of Alignment Collapse: When Fine-Tuning Breaks Safety</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15799v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Max Springer, Chung Peng Lee, Blossom Metevier, Jane Castleman, Bohdan Turbal, Hayoung Jung, Zeyu Shen, Aleksandra Korolova&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fine-tuning aligned language models on benign tasks unpredictably degrades safety guardrails, even when training data contains no harmful content and developers have no adversarial intent. We show that the prevailing explanation, that fine-tuning updates should be orthogonal to safety-critical directions in high-dimensional parameter space, offers false reassurance: we show this orthogonality is structurally unstable and collapses under the dynamics of gradient descent. We then resolve this through a novel geometric analysis, proving that alignment concentrates in low-dimensional subspaces wit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15799v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decision Quality Evaluation Framework at Pinterest</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15809v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yuqi Tian, Robert Paine, Attila Dobi, Kevin O'Sullivan, Aravindh Manickavasagam, Faisal Farooq&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Online platforms require robust systems to enforce content safety policies at scale. A critical component of these systems is the ability to evaluate the quality of moderation decisions made by both human agents and Large Language Models (LLMs). However, this evaluation is challenging due to the inherent trade-offs between cost, scale, and trustworthiness, along with the complexity of evolving policies&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15809v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:45:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-Agnostic Continual Learning for Chest Radiograph Classification</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15811v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Muthu Subash Kavitha, Anas Zafar, Amgad Muneer, Jia Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clinical deployment of chest radiograph classifiers requires models that can be updated as new datasets become available without retraining on previously ob- served data or degrading validated performance. We study, for the first time, a task-incremental continual learning setting for chest radiograph classification, in which heterogeneous chest X-ray datasets arrive sequentially and task identifiers are unavailable at inference. We propose a continual adapter-based routing learning strategy for Chest X-rays (CARL-XRay) that maintains a fixed high-capacity backbone and incrementally allocates &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15811v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:47:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Avey-B</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15814v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Devang Acharya, Mohammad Hammoud&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Compact pretrained bidirectional encoders remain the backbone of industrial NLP under tight compute and memory budgets. Their effectiveness stems from self-attention's ability to deliver high-quality bidirectional contextualization with sequence-level parallelism, as popularized by BERT-style architectures. Recently, Avey was introduced as an autoregressive, attention-free alternative that naturally admits an encoder-only adaptation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15814v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:50:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing AI Agents with Simulated Data: Why, what, and how?</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15816v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiaoran Liu, Istvan David&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As insufficient data volume and quality remain the key impediments to the adoption of modern subsymbolic AI, techniques of synthetic data generation are in high demand. Simulation offers an apt, systematic approach to generating diverse synthetic data. This chapter introduces the reader to the key concepts, benefits, and challenges of simulation-based synthetic data generation for AI training purposes, and to a reference framework to describe, design, and analyze digital twin-based AI simulation solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15816v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:53:27 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CrispEdit: Low-Curvature Projections for Scalable Non-Destructive LLM Editing</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15823v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zarif Ikram, Arad Firouzkouhi, Stephen Tu, Mahdi Soltanolkotabi, Paria Rashidinejad&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A central challenge in large language model (LLM) editing is capability preservation: methods that successfully change targeted behavior can quietly game the editing proxy and corrupt general capabilities, producing degenerate behaviors reminiscent of proxy/reward hacking. We present CrispEdit, a scalable and principled second-order editing algorithm that treats capability preservation as an explicit constraint, unifying and generalizing several existing editing approaches. CrispEdit formulates editing as constrained optimization and enforces the constraint by projecting edit updates onto the &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15823v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:58:04 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble-size-dependence of deep-learning post-processing methods that minimize an (un)fair score: motivating examples and a proof-of-concept solution</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15830v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Christopher David Roberts&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair scores reward ensemble forecast members that behave like samples from the same distribution as the verifying observations. They are therefore an attractive choice as loss functions to train data-driven ensemble forecasts or post-processing methods when large training ensembles are either unavailable or computationally prohibitive. The adjusted continuous ranked probability score (aCRPS) is fair and unbiased with respect to ensemble size, provided forecast members are exchangeable and interpretable as conditionally independent draws from an underlying predictive distribution&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2602.15830v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 18:59:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
