<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 03:15:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Spatio-Temporal Hierarchical Causal Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20558v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xintong Li, Haoran Zhang, Xiao Zhou&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The abundance of fine-grained spatio-temporal data, such as traffic sensor networks, offers vast opportunities for scientific discovery. However, inferring causal relationships from such observational data remains challenging, particularly due to unobserved confounders that are specific to units (e.g., geographical locations) yet influence outcomes over time. Most existing methods for spatio-temporal causal inference assume that all confounders are observed, an assumption that is often violated in practice&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20558v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 17:56:43 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PaTAS: A Parallel System for Trust Propagation in Neural Networks Using Subjective Logic</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20586v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Koffi Ismael Ouattara, Ioannis Krontiris, Theo Dimitrakos, Dennis Eisermann, Frank Kargl&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trustworthiness has become a key requirement for the deployment of artificial intelligence systems in safety-critical applications. Conventional evaluation metrics such as accuracy and precision fail to capture uncertainty or the reliability of model predictions, particularly under adversarial or degraded conditions. This paper introduces the \emph{Parallel Trust Assessment System (PaTAS)}, a framework for modeling and propagating trust in neural networks using Subjective Logic (SL)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20586v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:15:36 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EnergyTwin: A Multi-Agent System for Simulating and Coordinating Energy Microgrids</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20590v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jakub Muszyński, Ignacy Walużenicz, Patryk Zan, Zofia Wrona, Maria Ganzha, Marcin Paprzycki, Costin Bădică&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microgrids are deployed to reduce purchased grid energy, limit exposure to volatile tariffs, and ensure service continuity during disturbances. This requires coordinating heterogeneous distributed energy resources across multiple time scales and under variable conditions. Among existing tools, typically, power-system simulators capture physical behaviour but assume centralized control, while multi-agent frameworks model decentralized decision-making but represent energy with no physical grounding&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20590v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:19:40 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational bagging: a robust approach for Bayesian uncertainty quantification</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20594v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Shitao Fan, Ilsang Ohn, David Dunson, Lizhen Lin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Variational Bayes methods are popular due to their computational efficiency and adaptability to diverse applications. In specifying the variational family, mean-field classes are commonly used, which enables efficient algorithms such as coordinate ascent variational inference (CAVI) but fails to capture parameter dependence and typically underestimates uncertainty. In this work, we introduce a variational bagging approach that integrates a bagging procedure with variational Bayes, resulting in a bagged variational posterior for improved inference&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20594v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:24:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BrowseSafe: Understanding and Preventing Prompt Injection Within AI Browser Agents</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20597v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Kaiyuan Zhang, Mark Tenenholtz, Kyle Polley, Jerry Ma, Denis Yarats, Ninghui Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The integration of artificial intelligence (AI) agents into web browsers introduces security challenges that go beyond traditional web application threat models. Prior work has identified prompt injection as a new attack vector for web agents, yet the resulting impact within real-world environments remains insufficiently understood.   In this work, we examine the landscape of prompt injection attacks and synthesize a benchmark of attacks embedded in realistic HTML payloads&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20597v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:28:35 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Driver-Blindness Phenomenon: Why Deep Sequence Models Default to Autocorrelation in Blood Glucose Forecasting</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20601v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Heman Shakeri&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Deep sequence models for blood glucose forecasting consistently fail to leverage clinically informative drivers--insulin, meals, and activity--despite well-understood physiological mechanisms. We term this Driver-Blindness and formalize it via $Δ_{\text{drivers}}$, the performance gain of multivariate models over matched univariate baselines. Across the literature, $Δ_{\text{drivers}}$ is typically near zero&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20601v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:30:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Evaluating LLM Alignment by Evaluating LLMs as Judges</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20604v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yixin Liu, Pengfei Liu, Arman Cohan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alignment with human preferences is an important evaluation aspect of LLMs, requiring them to be helpful, honest, safe, and to precisely follow human instructions. Evaluating large language models' (LLMs) alignment typically involves directly assessing their open-ended responses, requiring human annotators or strong LLM judges. Conversely, LLMs themselves have also been extensively evaluated as judges for assessing alignment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20604v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:33:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to Purchase Labels? A Cost-Effective Approach Using Active Learning Markets</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20605v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Xiwen Huang, Pierre Pinson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We introduce and analyse active learning markets as a way to purchase labels, in situations where analysts aim to acquire additional data to improve model fitting, or to better train models for predictive analytics applications. This comes in contrast to the many proposals that already exist to purchase features and examples. By originally formalising the market clearing as an optimisation problem, we integrate budget constraints and improvement thresholds into the label acquisition process&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20605v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:34:33 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of Sums of Bivariate Functions: An Introduction to Relaxation-Based Methods for the Case of Finite Domains</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20607v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nils Müller&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We study the optimization of functions with $n&gt;2$ arguments that have a representation as a sum of several functions that have only $2$ of the $n$ arguments each, termed sums of bivariates, on finite domains. The complexity of optimizing sums of bivariates is shown to be NP-equivalent and it is shown that there exists free lunch in the optimization of sums of bivariates. Based on measure-valued extensions of the objective function, so-called relaxations, $\ell^2$-approximation, and entropy-regularization, we derive several tractable problem formulations solvable with linear programming, coordi&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20607v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:35:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building a Foundation Model for Trajectory from Scratch</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20610v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Gaspard Merten, Mahmoud Sakr, Gilles Dejaegere&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foundation models are transformative in artificial intelligence, but building them from scratch, especially for mobility trajectories, is not yet clear or documented. This tutorial bridges this gap by demonstrating the steps and code of a minimal implementation of a trajectory-focused foundation model starting from GPT-2. Through a concise, step-by-step, code-driven process, we demonstrate adapting GPT-2 for spatiotemporal data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20610v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:37:55 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can Vibe Coding Beat Graduate CS Students? An LLM vs. Human Coding Tournament on Market-driven Strategic Planning</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20613v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Panayiotis Danassis, Naman Goel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The rapid proliferation of Large Language Models (LLMs) has revolutionized AI-assisted code generation. This rapid development of LLMs has outpaced our ability to properly benchmark them. Prevailing benchmarks emphasize unit-test pass rates and syntactic correctness&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20613v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:40:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Performance of Deep Learning Models in Whole-body Dynamic 3D Posture Prediction During Load-reaching Activities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20615v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Seyede Niloofar Hosseini, Ali Mojibi, Mahdi Mohseni, Navid Arjmand, Alireza Taheri&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This study aimed to explore the application of deep neural networks for whole-body human posture prediction during dynamic load-reaching activities. Two time-series models were trained using bidirectional long short-term memory (BLSTM) and transformer architectures. The dataset consisted of 3D full-body plug-in gait dynamic coordinates from 20 normal-weight healthy male individuals each performing 204 load-reaching tasks from different load positions while adapting various lifting and handling techniques&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20615v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:40:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DiFR: Inference Verification Despite Nondeterminism</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20621v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Adam Karvonen, Daniel Reuter, Roy Rinberg, Luke Marks, Adrià Garriga-Alonso, Keri Warr&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As demand for LLM inference grows, it is becoming increasingly important that providers and their customers can verify that inference processes are performed correctly, without errors or tampering. However, re-running the same inference process twice often leads to different results due to benign numerical noise, making it difficult to distinguish legitimate variation from actual problems. To address this problem, we introduce Token-DiFR (Token-Divergence-From-Reference), a method for verifying inference outputs by comparing generated tokens against predictions made by a trusted reference impl&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20621v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:44:22 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Copyright Detection in Large Language Models: An Ethical Approach to Generative AI Development</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20623v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; David Szczecina, Senan Gaffori, Edmond Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The widespread use of Large Language Models (LLMs) raises critical concerns regarding the unauthorized inclusion of copyrighted content in training data. Existing detection frameworks, such as DE-COP, are computationally intensive, and largely inaccessible to independent creators. As legal scrutiny increases, there is a pressing need for a scalable, transparent, and user-friendly solution&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20623v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ROOT: Robust Orthogonalized Optimizer for Neural Network Training</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20626v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei He, Kai Han, Hang Zhou, Hanting Chen, Zhicheng Liu, Xinghao Chen, Yunhe Wang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The optimization of large language models (LLMs) remains a critical challenge, particularly as model scaling exacerbates sensitivity to algorithmic imprecision and training instability. Recent advances in optimizers have improved convergence efficiency through momentum orthogonalization, but suffer from two key robustness limitations: dimensional fragility in orthogonalization precision and vulnerability to outlier-induced noise. To address these robustness challenges, we introduce ROOT, a Robust Orthogonalized Optimizer that enhances training stability through dual robustness mechanisms&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20626v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:48:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fighting AI with AI: Leveraging Foundation Models for Assuring AI-Enabled Safety-Critical Systems</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20627v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Anastasia Mavridou, Divya Gopinath, Corina S. Păsăreanu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The integration of AI components, particularly Deep Neural Networks (DNNs), into safety-critical systems such as aerospace and autonomous vehicles presents fundamental challenges for assurance. The opacity of AI systems, combined with the semantic gap between high-level requirements and low-level network representations, creates barriers to traditional verification approaches. These AI-specific challenges are amplified by longstanding issues in Requirements Engineering, including ambiguity in natural language specifications and scalability bottlenecks in formalization&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20627v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:48:19 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MapReduce LoRA: Advancing the Pareto Front in Multi-Preference Optimization for Generative Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20629v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chieh-Yun Chen, Zhonghao Wang, Qi Chen, Zhifan Ye, Min Shi, Yue Zhao, Yinan Zhao, Hui Qu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reinforcement learning from human feedback (RLHF) with reward models has advanced alignment of generative models to human aesthetic and perceptual preferences. However, jointly optimizing multiple rewards often incurs an alignment tax, improving one dimension while degrading others. To address this, we introduce two complementary methods: MapReduce LoRA and Reward-aware Token Embedding (RaTE)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20629v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:49:21 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Collaboration in Multi-Agent Systems</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20639v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jiaru Zou, Xiyuan Yang, Ruizhong Qiu, Gaotang Li, Katherine Tieu, Pan Lu, Ke Shen, Hanghang Tong&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-agent systems (MAS) extend large language models (LLMs) from independent single-model reasoning to coordinative system-level intelligence. While existing LLM agents depend on text-based mediation for reasoning and communication, we take a step forward by enabling models to collaborate directly within the continuous latent space. We introduce LatentMAS, an end-to-end training-free framework that enables pure latent collaboration among LLM agents&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20639v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:56:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MotionV2V: Editing Motion in a Video</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20640v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ryan Burgert, Charles Herrmann, Forrester Cole, Michael S Ryoo, Neal Wadhwa, Andrey Voynov, Nataniel Ruiz&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;While generative video models have achieved remarkable fidelity and consistency, applying these capabilities to video editing remains a complex challenge. Recent research has explored motion controllability as a means to enhance text-to-video generation or image animation; however, we identify precise motion control as a promising yet under-explored paradigm for editing existing videos. In this work, we propose modifying video motion by directly editing sparse trajectories extracted from the input&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20640v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MedROV: Towards Real-Time Open-Vocabulary Detection Across Diverse Medical Imaging Modalities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20650v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Tooba Tehreem Sheikh, Jean Lahoud, Rao Muhammad Anwer, Fahad Shahbaz Khan, Salman Khan, Hisham Cholakkal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Traditional object detection models in medical imaging operate within a closed-set paradigm, limiting their ability to detect objects of novel labels. Open-vocabulary object detection (OVOD) addresses this limitation but remains underexplored in medical imaging due to dataset scarcity and weak text-image alignment. To bridge this gap, we introduce MedROV, the first Real-time Open Vocabulary detection model for medical imaging&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2511.20650v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 18:59:53 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
