<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>arXiv · 气象 × AI 精选论文</title>
    <link>https://example.github.io/arxiv-meteo-ai-rss/</link>
    <description>每日10:00自动更新 · 气象与AI交叉最新论文与要点</description>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <generator>python-feedgen</generator>
    <language>zh-CN</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 03:42:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Length Shift: Dynamic Outlier Truncation for Training Efficient Reasoning Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03969v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Wei Wu, Liyi Chen, Congxi Xiao, Tianfu Wang, Qimeng Wang, Chengqiang Lu, Yan Gao, Yi Wu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large reasoning models enhanced by reinforcement learning with verifiable rewards have achieved significant performance gains by extending their chain-of-thought. However, this paradigm incurs substantial deployment costs as models often exhibit excessive verbosity on simple queries. Existing efficient reasoning methods relying on explicit length penalties often introduce optimization conflicts and leave the generative mechanisms driving overthinking largely unexamined&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.03969v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 14:31:07 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Scheduling Framework for Efficient MoE Inference on Edge GPU-NDP Systems</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03992v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Qi Wu, Chao Fang, Jiayuan Chen, Ye Lin, Yueqi Zhang, Yichuan Bai, Yuan Du, Li Du&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mixture-of-Experts (MoE) models facilitate edge deployment by decoupling model capacity from active computation, yet their large memory footprint drives the need for GPU systems with near-data processing (NDP) capabilities that offload experts to dedicated processing units. However, deploying MoE models on such edge-based GPU-NDP systems faces three critical challenges: 1) severe load imbalance across NDP units due to non-uniform expert selection and expert parallelism, 2) insufficient GPU utilization during expert computation within NDP units, and 3) extensive data pre-profiling necessitated &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.03992v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 15:02:57 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Horizontal Discretization on Triangular and Hexagonal Grids on Linear Baroclinic and Symmetric Instabilities</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04013v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Steffen Maaß, Sergey Danilov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As global ocean general circulation models are run at eddy-permitting resolutions, reproducing accurate growth rates of baroclinic instabilities is a major concern when choosing a discretization of the equations of motion. From this viewpoint, we analyze discretizations on triangular and hexagonal grids with different types of variable staggering used in several ocean circulation models. By extending the linear baroclinic instability analysis in the Eady configuration to discretizations on more complex grids, several numerical subtleties are revealed&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04013v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 15:25:24 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HoneyTrap: Deceiving Large Language Model Attackers to Honeypot Traps with Resilient Multi-Agent Defense</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04034v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Siyuan Li, Xi Lin, Jun Wu, Zehao Liu, Haoyu Li, Tianjie Ju, Xiang Chen, Jianhua Li&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jailbreak attacks pose significant threats to large language models (LLMs), enabling attackers to bypass safeguards. However, existing reactive defense approaches struggle to keep up with the rapidly evolving multi-turn jailbreaks, where attackers continuously deepen their attacks to exploit vulnerabilities. To address this critical challenge, we propose HoneyTrap, a novel deceptive LLM defense framework leveraging collaborative defenders to counter jailbreak attacks&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04034v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 15:47:28 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MobileDreamer: Generative Sketch World Model for GUI Agent</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04035v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Yilin Cao, Yufeng Zhong, Zhixiong Zeng, Liming Zheng, Jing Huang, Haibo Qiu, Peng Shi, Wenji Mao&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Mobile GUI agents have shown strong potential in real-world automation and practical applications. However, most existing agents remain reactive, making decisions mainly from current screen, which limits their performance on long-horizon tasks. Building a world model from repeated interactions enables forecasting action outcomes and supports better decision making for mobile GUI agents&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04035v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 15:51:44 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ComfySearch: Autonomous Exploration and Reasoning for ComfyUI Workflows</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04060v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jinwei Su, Qizhen Lan, Zeyu Wang, Yinghui Xia, Hairu Wen, Yiqun Duan, Xi Xiao, Tianyu Shi&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI-generated content has progressed from monolithic models to modular workflows, especially on platforms like ComfyUI, allowing users to customize complex creative pipelines. However, the large number of components in ComfyUI and the difficulty of maintaining long-horizon structural consistency under strict graph constraints frequently lead to low pass rates and workflows of limited quality. To tackle these limitations, we present ComfySearch, an agentic framework that can effectively explore the component space and generate functional ComfyUI pipelines via validation-guided workflow construct&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04060v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:24:01 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mind the Generative Details: Direct Localized Detail Preference Optimization for Video Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04068v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zitong Huang, Kaidong Zhang, Yukang Ding, Chao Gao, Rui Ding, Ying Chen, Wangmeng Zuo&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aligning text-to-video diffusion models with human preferences is crucial for generating high-quality videos. Existing Direct Preference Otimization (DPO) methods rely on multi-sample ranking and task-specific critic models, which is inefficient and often yields ambiguous global supervision. To address these limitations, we propose LocalDPO, a novel post-training framework that constructs localized preference pairs from real videos and optimizes alignment at the spatio-temporal region level&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04068v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:32:17 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Reasoning Consistency in Large Multimodal Models under Cross-Modal Conflicts</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04073v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Zhihao Zhu, Jiafeng Liang, Shixin Jiang, Jinlan Fu, Ming Liu, Guanglu Sun, See-Kiong Ng, Bing Qin&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large Multimodal Models (LMMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities in video reasoning via Chain-of-Thought (CoT). However, the robustness of their reasoning chains remains questionable. In this paper, we identify a critical failure mode termed textual inertia, where once a textual hallucination occurs in the thinking process, models tend to blindly adhere to the erroneous text while neglecting conflicting visual evidence&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04073v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:39:34 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CSSG: Measuring Code Similarity with Semantic Graphs</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04085v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jingwen Xu, Yiyang Lu, Changze Lv, Zisu Huang, Zhengkang Guo, Zhengyuan Wang, Muzhao Tian, Xuanjing Huang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Existing code similarity metrics, such as BLEU, CodeBLEU, and TSED, largely rely on surface-level string overlap or abstract syntax tree structures, and often fail to capture deeper semantic relationships between programs.We propose CSSG (Code Similarity using Semantic Graphs), a novel metric that leverages program dependence graphs to explicitly model control dependencies and variable interactions, providing a semantics-aware representation of code.Experiments on the CodeContests+ dataset show that CSSG consistently outperforms existing metrics in distinguishing more similar code from less si&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04085v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 16:54:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layer-wise Positional Bias in Short-Context Language Modeling</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04098v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Maryam Rahimi, Mahdi Nouri, Yadollah Yaghoobzadeh&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Language models often show a preference for using information from specific positions in the input regardless of semantic relevance. While positional bias has been studied in various contexts, from attention sinks to task performance degradation in long-context settings, prior work has not established how these biases evolve across individual layers and input positions, or how they vary independent of task complexity. We introduce an attribution-based framework to analyze positional effects in short-context language modeling&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04098v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:04:30 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Impact of Modules and Their Interactions in the PSO-X Framework</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04100v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Christian L. Camacho-Villalón, Ana Nikolikj, Katharina Dost, Eva Tuba, Sašo Džeroski, Tome Eftimov&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The PSO-X framework incorporates dozens of modules that have been proposed for solving single-objective continuous optimization problems using particle swarm optimization. While modular frameworks enable users to automatically generate and configure algorithms tailored to specific optimization problems, the complexity of this process increases with the number of modules in the framework and the degrees of freedom defined for their interaction. Understanding how modules affect the performance of algorithms for different problems is critical to making the process of finding effective implementat&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04100v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InfiniteWeb: Scalable Web Environment Synthesis for GUI Agent Training</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04126v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Ziyun Zhang, Zezhou Wang, Xiaoyi Zhang, Zongyu Guo, Jiahao Li, Bin Li, Yan Lu&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;GUI agents that interact with graphical interfaces on behalf of users represent a promising direction for practical AI assistants. However, training such agents is hindered by the scarcity of suitable environments. We present InfiniteWeb, a system that automatically generates functional web environments at scale for GUI agent training&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04126v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:40:08 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pixel-Wise Multimodal Contrastive Learning for Remote Sensing Images</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04127v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Leandro Stival, Ricardo da Silva Torres, Helio Pedrini&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Satellites continuously generate massive volumes of data, particularly for Earth observation, including satellite image time series (SITS). However, most deep learning models are designed to process either entire images or complete time series sequences to extract meaningful features for downstream tasks. In this study, we propose a novel multimodal approach that leverages pixel-wise two-dimensional (2D) representations to encode visual property variations from SITS more effectively&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;br/&gt;- 任务：降尺度/预报/临近预测等应用场景。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04127v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:41:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ContextFocus: Activation Steering for Contextual Faithfulness in Large Language Models</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04131v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Nikhil Anand, Shwetha Somasundaram, Anirudh Phukan, Apoorv Saxena, Koyel Mukherjee&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs) encode vast amounts of parametric knowledge during pre-training. As world knowledge evolves, effective deployment increasingly depends on their ability to faithfully follow externally retrieved context. When such evidence conflicts with the model's internal knowledge, LLMs often default to memorized facts, producing unfaithful outputs&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04131v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:45:20 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wow, wo, val! A Comprehensive Embodied World Model Evaluation Turing Test</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04137v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Chun-Kai Fan, Xiaowei Chi, Xiaozhu Ju, Hao Li, Yong Bao, Yu-Kai Wang, Lizhang Chen, Zhiyuan Jiang&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As world models gain momentum in Embodied AI, an increasing number of works explore using video foundation models as predictive world models for downstream embodied tasks like 3D prediction or interactive generation. However, before exploring these downstream tasks, video foundation models still have two critical questions unanswered: (1) whether their generative generalization is sufficient to maintain perceptual fidelity in the eyes of human observers, and (2) whether they are robust enough to serve as a universal prior for real-world embodied agents. To provide a standardized framework for &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04137v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 17:50:37 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Theoretical and Empirical Taxonomy of Imbalance in Binary Classification</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04149v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Rose Yvette Bandolo Essomba, Ernest Fokoué&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Class imbalance significantly degrades classification performance, yet its effects are rarely analyzed from a unified theoretical perspective. We propose a principled framework based on three fundamental scales: the imbalance coefficient $η$, the sample--dimension ratio $κ$, and the intrinsic separability $Δ$. Starting from the Gaussian Bayes classifier, we derive closed-form Bayes errors and show how imbalance shifts the discriminant boundary, yielding a deterioration slope that predicts four regimes: Normal, Mild, Extreme, and Catastrophic&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04149v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:02:11 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Klear: Unified Multi-Task Audio-Video Joint Generation</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04151v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Jun Wang, Chunyu Qiang, Yuxin Guo, Yiran Wang, Xijuan Zeng, Chen Zhang, Pengfei Wan&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Audio-video joint generation has progressed rapidly, yet substantial challenges still remain. Non-commercial approaches still suffer audio-visual asynchrony, poor lip-speech alignment, and unimodal degradation, which can be stemmed from weak audio-visual correspondence modeling, limited generalization, and scarce high-quality dense-caption data. To address these issues, we introduce Klear and delve into three axes--model architecture, training strategy, and data curation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04151v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:03:45 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clinical Data Goes MEDS? Let's OWL make sense of it</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04164v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Alberto Marfoglia, Jong Ho Jhee, Adrien Coulet&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The application of machine learning on healthcare data is often hindered by the lack of standardized and semantically explicit representation, leading to limited interoperability and reproducibility across datasets and experiments. The Medical Event Data Standard (MEDS) addresses these issues by introducing a minimal, event-centric data model designed for reproducible machine-learning workflows from health data. However, MEDS is defined as a data-format specification and does not natively provide integration with the Semantic Web ecosystem&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 数据：包含再分析/卫星/观测等来源。&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04164v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agent Drift: Quantifying Behavioral Degradation in Multi-Agent LLM Systems Over Extended Interactions</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04170v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Abhishek Rath&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Multi-agent Large Language Model (LLM) systems have emerged as powerful architectures for complex task decomposition and collaborative problem-solving. However, their long-term behavioral stability remains largely unexamined. This study introduces the concept of agent drift, defined as the progressive degradation of agent behavior, decision quality, and inter-agent coherence over extended interaction sequences&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 方法：采用机器学习/深度学习模型。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04170v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:37:26 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedding Autonomous Agents in Resource-Constrained Robotic Platforms</title>
      <link>http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.04191v1</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Authors:&lt;/b&gt; Negar Halakou, Juan F. Gutierrez, Ye Sun, Han Jiang, Xueming Wu, Yilun Song, Andres Gomez&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many embedded devices operate under resource constraints and in dynamic environments, requiring local decision-making capabilities. Enabling devices to make independent decisions in such environments can improve the responsiveness of the system and reduce the dependence on constant external control. In this work, we integrate an autonomous agent, programmed using AgentSpeak, with a small two-wheeled robot that explores a maze using its own decision-making and sensor data&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;要点：&lt;br/&gt;- 摘要未提供更多细节，建议阅读原文。&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">2601.04191v1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 18:57:32 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
